[Music]
this is a three it's sloppily written
and rendered at an extremely low
resolution of 28x 28 pixels but your
brain has no trouble recognizing it as a
three and I want you to take a moment to
appreciate how crazy it is that brains
can do this so effortlessly I mean this
this and this are also recognizable as
threes even though the specific values
of each pixel is very different from one
image to the next the particular light
sensitive cells in your eye that are
firing when you see this three are very
different from the ones firing when you
see this three but something in that
crazy smart visual cortex of yours
resolves these as representing the same
idea while at the same time recognizing
other images as their own distinct ideas
but if I told you hey sit down and write
for me a program that takes in a grid of
28x 28 pixels like this and outputs a
single number between 0 and 10 telling
you what it thinks the digit is well the
task goes from comically trivial to
dauntingly difficult unless you've been
living under a rock I think I hardly
need to motivate the relevance and
importance of machine learning and
neural networks to the present and to
the future but what I want to do here is
show you what a neural network actually
is assuming no background and to help
visualize what it's doing not as a
buzzword but as a piece of math my hope
is just that you come away feeling like
the structure itself is motivated and to
feel like you know what it means when
you read or you hear about a neural
network quote unquote learning this
video is just going to be devoted to the
structure component of that and the
following one is going to tackle
learning what we're going to do is put
together a neural network that can learn
to recognize handwritten
digits this is a somewhat classic
example for introducing the topic and
I'm happy to stick with the status quo
here because at the end of the two
videos I want to point you to a couple
good resources where you can learn more
and where you can download the code that
does this and play with it on your own
computer there are many many variants of
neural networks and in recent years
there's been sort of a boom in research
towards these variants but in these two
introductory videos you and I are just
going to look at the simplest plain
vanilla form with no added Frills this
is kind of a necessary prerequisite for
understanding any of the more powerful
modern variants and trust me it still
has plenty of complexity for us to wrap
our minds around but even in this
simplest form it can learn to recognize
handwritten digits which is a pretty
cool thing for a computer to be able to
do and at the same time you'll see how
it does fall short of a couple hopes
that we might have for
it as the name suggests neural networks
are inspired by the brain but let's
break that down what are the neurons and
in what sense are they linked together
right now when I say neuron all I want
you to think about is a thing that holds
a number specifically a number between Z
0 and 1 it's really not more than
that for example the network starts with
a bunch of neurons corresponding to each
of the 28 * 28 pixels of the input image
which is 784 neurons in total each one
of these holds a number that represents
the grayscale value of the corresponding
pixel ranging from zero for black pixels
up to one for white pixels this number
inside the neuron is called its
activation and the image you might have
in mind here is that each neuron is lit
up when its activation is a high
number so all of these 784 neurons make
up the first layer of our
Network now jumping over to the last
layer this has 10 neurons each
representing one of the digits the
activation in these neurons again some
number that's between 0 and one
represents how much the system thinks
that a given image corresponds with a
given digit there's also a couple layers
in between called The Hidden layers
which for the time being should just be
a giant question mark for how on Earth
this process of recognizing digits is
going to be handled in this network I
chose two hidden layers each one with 16
neurons and admittedly that's kind of an
arbitrary choice to be honest I chose
two layers based on how I want to
motivate the structure in just a moment
and 16 well that was just a nice number
to fit on the screen in practice there
is a lot lot of room for experiment with
a specific structure here the way the
network operates activations in one
layer determine the activations of the
next layer and of course the heart of
the network as an information processing
mechanism comes down to exactly how
those activations from one layer bring
about activations in the next layer it's
meant to be Loosely analogous to how in
biological networks of neurons some
groups of neurons firing cause certain
others to fire now the network I'm
showing here has already been trained to
recognize digits and let me show you
what I mean by that it means if you feed
in an image lighting up all 784 neurons
of the input layer according to the
brightness of each pixel in the image
that pattern of activations causes some
very specific pattern in the next layer
which causes some pattern in the one
after it which finally gives some
pattern in the output layer and the
brightest neuron of that output layer is
the Network's choice so to speak for
what digit this image represents
and before jumping into the math for how
one layer influences the next or how
training Works let's just talk about why
it's even reasonable to expect a layered
structure like this to behave
intelligently what are we expecting here
what is the best hope for what those
middle layers might be doing well when
you or I recognize digits we piece
together various components a nine has a
loop up top and a line on the right an
eight also has a loop up top but it's
paired with another loop down low a four
basically breaks down into three
specific lines and things like that now
in a perfect world we might hope that
each neuron in the second to last layer
corresponds with one of these
subcomponents that anytime you feed in
an image with say a loop up top like a 9
or an eight there's some specific neuron
whose activation is going to be close to
one and I don't mean this specific Loop
of pixels the hope would be that any
generally loopy pattern to WS the top
sets off this neuron that way going from
the third layer to the last one just
requires learning which combination of
subcomponents corresponds to which
digits of course that just kicks the
problem down the road because how would
you recognize these subcomponents or
even learn what the right subcomponents
should be and I still haven't even
talked about how one layer influences
the next but run with me on this one for
a moment recognizing a loop can also
break down into sub problems one
reasonable way to do this would be to
First recognize the various little edges
that make it up similarly a long line
like the kind you might see in the
digits one or four or seven well that's
really just a long Edge or maybe you
think of it as a certain pattern of
several smaller edges so maybe our hope
is that each neuron in the second layer
of the network corresponds with the
various relevant little edges maybe when
an image like this one comes in it
lights up all of the neurons associated
with a around 8 to 10 specific little
edges which in turn lights up the
neurons associated with the upper Loop
and a long vertical line and those light
up the neuron associated with a nine
whether or not this is what our final
Network actually does is another
question one that I'll come back to once
we see how to train the network but this
is a hope that we might have a sort of
goal with the layered structure like
this moreover you can imagine how being
able to detect edges and patterns like
this would be really useful for other
image recog tasks and even Beyond image
recognition there are all sorts of
intelligent things you might want to do
that break down into layers of
abstraction parsing speech for example
involves taking raw audio and picking
out distinct sounds which combine to
make certain syllables which combine to
form words which combine to make up
phrases and more abstract thoughts Etc
but getting back to how any of this
actually works picture yourself right
now designing how exactly the
activations in one layer might determine
the activ in the next the goal is to
have some mechanism that could
conceivably combine pixels into edges or
edges into patterns or patterns into
digits and to zoom in on one very
specific example let's say the hope is
for one particular neuron in the second
layer to pick up on whether or not the
image has an edge in this region here
the question at hand is what parameters
should the network have what dials and
knobs should you be able to tweak so
that it's Express iive enough to
potentially capture this pattern or any
other pixel pattern or the pattern that
several edges can make a loop and other
such things Well what we'll do is assign
a weight to each one of the connections
between our neuron and the neurons from
the first layer these weights are just
numbers then take all of those
activations from the first layer and
compute their weighted sum according to
these
weights I find it helpful to think of
these weights as being being organized
into a little grid of their own and I'm
going to use green pixels to indicate
positive weights and red pixels to
indicate negative weights where the
brightness of that pixel is some loose
depiction of the weights value now if we
made the weights associated with almost
all of the pixel zero except for some
positive weights in this region that we
care about then taking the weighted sum
of all the pixel values really just
amounts to adding up the values of the
pixel just in the region that we care
about and if if you really wanted to
pick up on whether there's an edge here
what you might do is have some negative
weights associated with the surrounding
pixels then the sum is largest when
those middle pixels are bright but the
surrounding pixels are
darker when you compute a weighted sum
like this you might come out with any
number but for this network what we want
is for activations to be some value
between 0o and one so a common thing to
do is to pump this weighted sum into
some function that squishes the real
number number line into the range
between 0 and 1 and a common function
that does this is called the sigmoid
function also known as a logistic curve
basically very negative inputs end up
close to zero very positive inputs end
up close to one and it just steadily
increases around the input
zero so the activation of the neuron
here is basically a measure of how
positive the relevant weighted sum
is but maybe it's not that you want the
neuron to light up when the weighted sum
is bigger than zero maybe you only want
it to be active when the sum is bigger
than say 10 that is you want some bias
for it to be
inactive what we'll do then is just add
in some other number like -10 to this
weighted sum before plugging it through
the sigmoid squish ification function
that additional number is called the
bias so the weights tell you what pixel
pattern this neuron in the second layer
is picking up on and the bias tells you
how high the weighted sum needs to be
before the neuron starts getting
meaningfully active and that is just one
neuron every other neuron in this layer
is going to be connected to all 784
pixel neurons from the first layer and
each one of those 784 connections has
its own weight associated with it also
each one has some bias some other number
that you add on to the weighted sum
before squishing it with the sigmoid and
that's a lot to think about about with
this hidden layer of 16 neurons that's a
total of 784 * 16 weights along with 16
biases and all of that is just the
connections from the first layer to the
second the connections between the other
layers also have a bunch of weights and
biases associated with them all said and
done this network has almost exactly
13,000 total weights and biases 13,000
knobs and dials that can be tweaked and
turned to make this network behave and
different ways so when we talk about
learning what that's referring to is
getting the computer to find a valid
setting for all of these many many
numbers so that it'll actually solve the
problem at
hand one thought experiment that is at
once fun and kind of horrifying is to
imagine sitting down and setting all of
these weights and biases by hand
purposefully tweaking the numbers so
that the second layer picks up on edges
the third layer picks up on patterns Etc
I personally find this satisfying rather
rather than just treating the network as
a total Black Box because when the
network doesn't perform the way you
anticipate if you've built up a little
bit of a relationship with what those
weights and biases actually mean you
have a starting place for experimenting
with how to change the structure to
improve or when the network does work
but not for the reasons you might expect
digging into what the weights and biases
are doing is a good way to challenge
your assumptions and really expose the
full space of possible
solutions by the way the actual function
here is a little cumbersome to write
down don't you
think so let me show you a more
notationally compact way that these
connections are represented this is how
you'd see it if you choose to read up
more about neural networks organize all
of the activations from one layer into a
column as a
vector then organize all of the weights
as a matrix where each row of that
Matrix corresponds to the connections
between one layer and a particular
neuron in the next layer what that means
is that taking the weighted sum of the
activations in the first layer according
to these weights corresponds to one of
the terms in the Matrix Vector product
of everything we have on the left
here by the way so much of machine
learning just comes down to having a
good grasp of linear algebra so for any
of you who want a nice visual
understanding for matrices and what
Matrix Vector multiplication means take
a look at the series I did on linear
algebra especially chapter 3 back to our
expression instead of talking about
adding the bias to each one of these
values independently we represent it by
organizing all those biases into a
vector and adding the entire Vector to
the previous Matrix Vector product then
as a final step I'll wrap a sigmoid
around the outside here and what that's
supposed to represent is that you're
going to apply the sigmoid function to
each specific component of the resulting
Vector
inside so once you write down this
weight Matrix and these vectors as their
own symbols you can communicate the full
transition of activations from one layer
to the next in an extremely tight and
neat little expression and this makes
the relevant code both a lot simpler and
a lot faster since many libraries
optimize the heck out of matrix
multiplication remember how earlier I
said these neurons are simply things
that hold numbers well of course the
specific numbers that they hold depends
on the image you feed
in so it's actually more accurate to
think of each neuron as a function one
that takes in the outputs of all the
neurons in the previous layer and spits
out a number between 0 and one really
the entire network is just a function
one that takes in 784 numbers as an
input and spits out 10 numbers as an
output it's an absurdly complicated
function one that involves 13,000
parameters in the forms of these weights
and biases that pick up on certain
patterns and which involves iterating
many Matrix Vector products and the
sigmo squish ification function but it's
just a function nonetheless and in a way
it's kind of reassuring that it looks
complicated I mean if it were any
simpler what hope would we have that it
could take on the challenge of
recognizing digits and how does it take
on that challenge how does this network
learn the appropriate weights and biases
just by looking at data well that's what
I'll show in the next video and I'll
also dig a little more into what this
particular Network we're seeing is
really
doing now is the point I suppose I
should say say subscribe to stay
notified about when that video or any
new videos come out but realistically
most of you don't actually receive
notifications from YouTube do you maybe
more honestly I should say subscribe so
that the neural networks that underly
YouTube's recommendation algorithm are
primed to believe that you want to see
content from this channel get
recommended to you anyway stay posted
for more thank you very much to everyone
supporting these videos on patreon I've
been a little slow to progress in the
probability Series this summer but I'm
jumping back into it after this project
so patrons you can look out for updates
there to close things off here I have
with me Lea Lee who did her PhD work on
the theoretical side of deep learning
and who currently works at a venture
capital firm called amplify Partners who
kindly provided some of the funding for
this video so Leisa one thing I think we
should quickly bring up is this sigmoid
function as I understand it early
networks use this to squish the relevant
weighted sum into that interval between
0 and one you know kind of motivated by
this biological analogy of neurons
either being in active or active exactly
but relatively few modern networks
actually use sigmoid anymore that's kind
of old school right yeah or rather reu
seems to be much easier to train and reu
reu stands for rectified linear unit yes
it's this kind of function where you
just taking a Max of zero and a where a
is given by what you were explaining in
the video and what this was sort of
motivated from I think was a partially
by a biological analogy with how neurons
would either be activated or not and so
if it passes a certain threshold it
would be the identity function but if it
did not then it would just not be
activated so it be zero so it's kind of
a simplification using sigmoids didn't
help training or it was very difficult
to train it's at some point and people
just tried ra you and it happened to
work very well for these incredibly um
deep neural networks all right thank you
Alicia
[Music]